Guide to the William Pierrepont White collection, 1728-1939.
White, William Pierrepont collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
William Pierrepont White collection, 1728-1939.
399
White, William Pierrepont.
63.6 cubic ft.
Correspondence, diaries, financial and legal documents.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, diaries, deeds, accounts, maps, surveys, pamphlets, statements, registers, bills, land contracts, inventories, cashbooks, indentures, minutes, and other records and papers reflecting the westward and southward movement of members of the White and related families.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, diaries, deeds, accounts, maps, surveys, pamphlets, statements, registers, bills, land contracts, inventories, cashbooks, indentures, minutes, and other records and papers reflecting the westward and southward movement of members of the White and related families, concerning their activities in the development of land, canals, railroads, cotton manufacturing, mining, banking, and highways, chiefly in New York State. The early papers relate to the White family of Middletown, Connecticut, and the development after 1783 of Whitestown, New York, and include the town books (1807-1823) for Richland, New York, church records, early election returns, deeds, documents on the Brothertown Indians, grist mills, civil and criminal cases, slave sales, the War of 1812, the Bank of Utica, and the Pierrepont Land Office. Includes the diary of William Pierrepont White. One group of papers relates to the disposal of the Constable lands and the development of Pierrepont Manor, and contains statements of land contracts (1801-1810) given by William Constable, an inventory of the Constable estate (1829), a memorandum of journeys made by William Constable Pierrepont to the Constable tract, lists of bonds for Ellisburgh, New York (1834-1841), and a series of letters from Franklin B. Hough relating to life boats for Ellisburgh and Oswego, and to other matters.
Also, correspondence, accounts, and other documents of Hugh White, son of the Whitestown proprietor and early concrete manufacturer.
Other papers concern Canvass White, an engineer for the Erie Canal, construction superintendent for the Union Canal of Pennsylvania, the Delaware and Raritan Canal of New Jersey, and the New York Water Works Company, and promoter of the Cohoes Company. Includes the papers of William N. White, vice-president of the Utica Pipe Foundry Company, director of the Utica and Mohawk Railroad Company, of the Jefferson County National Bank, the Rome, Watertown, and Ogdensburg Railroad Company, and other companies; he was the manager of the estate of his father-in-law, William Constable Pierrepont, and an active figure in political, church, and educational affairs. Also the papers of William Pierrepont White, lawyer and businessman of New York and Utica, president of the Oneida Historical Society, and a pioneer in the development of modern highways. Includes papers of the Wheeler, Constable, and Van Wagenen papers, as well as other families; also, Walcott family correspondence beginning with a series of letters (1825-1827) from Walnut Hills, Mississippi, and other series relating to real estate speculation in Kansas, Missouri, Indiana, and Nebraska, to banking in North Dakota, to the management of cotton mills in Georgia and New York, and to oil and mining interests.
SUBJECTS
Names:
White, William Pierrepont.; Constable family.; Constable, William.; Hough, Franklin B.; Pierrepont, William Constable.; Van Wagner family; Walcott family.; Wheeler family.; White family.; White, Canvass; White, Hugh; White, William N.; Bank of Utica (Utica, N.Y.); Cohoes Company.; Delaware and Raritan Canal (N.J.); Erie Canal.; Jefferson County National Bank (Jefferson County, N.Y.); New York (State). Legislature.; New-York Water Works Company; Oneida Historical Society at Utica; Pierrepont Land Office.; Rome, Watertown, and Ogdensburg Railroad Company.; Union Canal (Penn.); Utica and Mohawk Railroad Company.
Subjects:
Real property -- New York (State); Land titles -- New York (State); Real property -- Kansas.; Real property -- Missouri.; Real property -- Indiana.; Real property -- Nebraska.; Canals -- New York (State); Canals -- New Jersey.; Canals -- Pennsylvania.; Railroads -- New York (State); Cotton manufacture -- New York (State); Cotton manufacture -- Georgia.; Textile factories -- New York (State) -- Oneida County.; Textile factories -- Georgia.; Mineral industries -- New York (State); Banks and banking -- New York (State) -- Oneida County.; Banks and banking -- North Dakota.; Roads -- Design and construction -- New York (State); Elections -- New York (State) -- Oneida County.; Brotherton Indians.; Grist mills -- New York (State) -- Oneida County.; Slavery -- New York (State); Life-boats -- New York (State) -- Lake Ontario.; Concrete.; Woolen goods.; Education -- New York (State) -- Oneida County.; Oil industries -- New York (State); Emigration and immigration.; Families -- New York (State) -- Oneida County.; Migration, Internal -- United States.; Engineers.; Bankers.; Bankers; Banks and banking; Brotherton Indians; Canals; Commerce; Concrete; Cotton manufacture; Economics; Education; Elections; Emigration and immigration; Engineers; Families; Gristmills; Industries; Land titles; Lifeboats; Migration, Internal; Mineral industries; Oil industries; Political science; Railroads; Real property; Roads -- Design and construction; Slavery; Textile factories; Woolen goods
Places:
Oneida County (N.Y.) -- Commerce.; Oneida County (N.Y.) -- Economic aspects.; Oneida County (N.Y.) -- Industries.; Oneida County (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; Oneida County (N.Y.) -- Religious life and customs.; New York (State) -- Commerce.; Whitestown (N.Y.) -- History, Local.; Georgia; Indiana; Kansas; Missouri; Nebraska; New Jersey; New York (State); New York (State) -- Oneida County; North Dakota; Pennsylvania; United States
Form and Genre Terms:
Deeds.; Maps.; Surveys.; Inventories.; Cashbooks.; Account books.; Inventories.; Local history
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Consists of collections #399, #565, #586, and #944.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Walcott Papers
Series III. Newspaper Clippings
Series IV. Assorted Materials
Series V. Unprocessed Materials
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence
  - 1728-1827 correspondence, 1728-1827 (Box 1 399)
  - Letter from E.D. and Charlotte Walcott to Hugh White, 1820-02-05; Walcott, E.D.; Walcott, Charlotte (Box 1 399)
    Brother
    White, Hugh
    Walnut Hills, Mississippi
    Whitesboro, New York
  - Letter from E.D. and Charlotte Walcott to Hugh White, 1825-01-28; Walcott, E.D.; Walcott, Charlotte (Box 1 399)
    Father
    Utica
  - Letter from E.D. Walcott to Hugh White, 1826-02-28; Walcott, E.D. (Box 1 399)
    Shrewsbury, New Jersey
  - Letter from E.D. Walcott to Hugh White, 1829-12-22; Walcott, E.D. (Box 1 399)
  - Letter from E.D. Walcott to Hugh White, 1827-08-07; Walcott, E.D. (Box 1 399)
    Chittenango, New York
  - Letter from E.D. Walcott to Hugh White, 1827-09-11; Walcott, E.D. (Box 1 399)
  - Letter from E.D. Walcott to Hugh White, 1827-10-30; Walcott, E.D. (Box 1 399)
  - Letter from E.D. Walcott to Hugh White, 1827-11-28; Walcott, E.D. (Box 1 399)
  - Letter from Sofia Duston to Hugh White, 1825-01-24; Duston, Sofia (Box 1 399)
    Petit Saw Bluff, Missouri
  - Letter from John Duston to Canvass White, 1827-08-24; Duston, John (Box 1 399)
    White, Canvass
  - Letter from John Duston to Hugh White and Susan Porter, 1827-08-25; Duston, John (Box 1 399)
    Porter, Susan
  - Letter from John Duston to Hugh White, 1818-07-16; Duston, John (Box 1 399)
    Duston, Sofia
    Franklin, Missouri
    Whitestown, New York
  - Letter from John Duston to Hugh White, 1819-07-26; Duston, John (Box 1 399)
  - Two letters from Rufus Easton to Hugh White, 1805-07; Easton, Rufus (Box 1 399)
    St. Louis
  - 1828-1869 correspondence, 1828-1869 (Box 2 399)
  - Letter from Robert White to Hugh White, 1829-09-04; White, Robert (Box 2 399)
    Dustin, Sofia
    Chittenango
  - Letter from Robert White to Hugh White, 1830-06-20; White, Robert (Box 2 399)
  - Good Roads correspondence, 1903, 1926-1928 (Box 65 399)
  - Correspondence, 1910-1912, 1915 (Box 69 399)
- Walcott Papers
  - Walcott papers, 1896-1898 (Box 3 399)
  - Walcott papers, 1902-1903 (Box 4 399)
  - Walcott papers, 1899-1901 (Box 5 399)
  - Walcott papers, 1904-1929 (Box 6 399)
  - Walcott papers, 1892-1893-05 (Box 66 399)
  - Walcott papers, 1894-1895-05 (Box 67 399)
- Newspaper Clippings
  - Newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 7 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 8 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 9 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 10 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 11 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 12 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 13 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 14 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 15 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 16 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 17 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 18 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 19 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 20 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 21 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 22 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 23 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 24 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 25 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 26 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 27 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 28 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 29 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 30 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 31 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 32 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 33 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 34 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 35 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 36 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 37 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 38 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 39 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 40 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 41 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 42 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 43 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 44 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 45 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 46 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 47 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 48 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 49 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 50 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 51 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 52 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 53 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 54 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 55 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 56 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 57 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 58 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 59 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 60 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 61 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 62 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 63 399)
  - Mostly newspaper clippings, Date Unknown (Box 64 399)
- Assorted Materials
  - Receipt for $1985 received by E.D. White, 1827-08-07 (Box 1 399)
  - 1902 (Box 68 399)
  - 1913-1914 (Box 70 399)
  - 1922-1923 (Box 71 399)
  - 1928-1934 (Box 72 399)
  - 1925 (Box 73 399)
  - Utica Tool, 1903-1915 (Box 74 399)
  - Utica Tool, 1921-1927 (Box 75 399)
  - Utica Tool, 1916-1920 (Box 76 399)
  - Crow Holl, 1900-1913 (Box 77 399)
  - Invitations, Date Unknown (Box 78 399)
  - Crow Holl, 1914-1915, 1922-1923 (Box 79 399)
  - Cash and Securities, C.A. Van Waganen, 1895-1968 (Box 80 399)
  - Printed Matter, Date Unknown (Box 81 399)
  - W.P. White's societies, Date Unknown (Box 82 399)
  - Copy of 1792 Indenture No. 3, 1815 (Box 1 944, Folder 1)
  - Copy of 1792 Indenture No. 4, 1815 (Box 1 944, Folder 2)
  - Copy of 1794 Indenture No. 5, 1815 (Box 1 944, Folder 3)
  - Copy of 1794 Indenture No. 6, 1815 (Box 1 944, Folder 4)
  - Copy of 1794 Indenture No. 7, 1815 (Box 1 944, Folder 5)
  - Copy of 1796 Indenture No. 8, 1815 (Box 1 944, Folder 6)
  - Copies of 1795 Field Books, Undated (Box 1 944, Folder 7)
  - Woodhull and Scriba's Patents, 1801, 1807, 1817 (Box 1 944, Folder 8)
  - Fonda's Patent, 1801, 1814, 1818 (Box 1 944, Folder 9)
  - Surveys, Undated (Box 1 944, Folder 10)
  - Field Books (19 Envelopes), 1793-1831; 19 envelopes (Box 2 944)
  - Miscellany (1 Envelope), 1819 (Box 2 944)
  - Register of Notes and Due Bills belonging to William Constable Pierrepont (1 Volume), 1840 (Box 2 944)
  - Surveys and Maps, Undated (Box 3 944)
  - Charles H. Cross' "D" Daily Journal, 1863; Cross, Charles H. (Box 4 944)
  - Alphabetical Index, 1863 (Box 4 944)
  - Workbook "No. 7" Mr. Thompsons evening lessons, 1818 (Box 4 944)
  - Workbook "No. 7", 1819 (Box 4 944)
  - Traverse Tables, Undated (Box 4 944)
  - Traverse Tables (mss.), 1821 (Box 4 944)
  - Report of the Different Routes and Estimates of the Sacketts Harbor and Saratoga Railroad Co. Members, 1852 (Box 5 944)
  - Benjamin Wright's original (?) book of Lorraine No. 1, 1815; Wright, Benjamin (Box 5 944)
  - Orwell No. 11, 1829 (Box 5 944)
  - Township No. 10, 1805-1822 (Box 5 944)
  - Township No. 9, 1814-1819 (Box 5 944)
  - A Survey of Town No. 10 Boyleston Tract, 1797 (Box 5 944)
  - Field Book of Resurvey of Lot Lines in Township No. 1 of Lorraine by Benjamin Hadley in 1832 and 1833, Undated (Box 5 944)
  - Cash Book, 1878-1887 (Box 5 944)
  - Various plans and maps, Undated (Map-case 1)
- Unprocessed Materials
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 83 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 84 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 85 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 86 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 87 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 88 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 89 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 90 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 91 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 92 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 93 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 94 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 95 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 96 399)
  - Unprocessed materials, Date Unknown (Box 97 399)